Finding Aid for George Uhlenbeck Papers 1918-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Uhlenbeck Papers 1918-1982, 1925-1970
Uhlenbeck, George Eugène, 1900-1988.
7 linear feet
Physicist, professor of physics at the University of Michigan and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology; correspondence, lectures and speeches, publications, notebooks, research papers, and topical files.
945 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was acquired on September 15, 1993, from Mrs. Else R. Uhlenbeck (Donor No. 8182 ). Additional papers came to the library in 1998. A small accession was received in 2002.
The collection is open for research.
George Eugène Uhlenbeck was born on 6 December 1900, in Batavia, Java, Dutch East Indies [now Jakarta, Indonesia]. In 1907 the family returned to the Netherlands, settling permanently in the Hague.
Uhlenbeck showed an early, self-directed interest in physics, attracting the attention of his high school physics instructor. Because a Dutch law required entering university students to have training in Latin and Greek, Uhlenbeck enrolled as an engineering student at the Technische Hogeschool at Delft in September 1918. A propitious change in the law allowed him, in January 1919, to begin studies in physics and mathematics at the University of Leiden.
In 1920, Uhlenbeck began attending seminars at Leiden given by the physicist Paul Ehrenfest, who was to become his primary scientific mentor. From 1922 to 1925 he spent summers in Holland and the remainder of the year in Rome, serving as tutor for the son of J. H. van Royen, the Dutch ambassador there. While in Rome he attended mathematics courses given by Enriques, Levi-Civita, and Volterra. In 1923 he met Enrico Fermi and established a contact between Ehrenfest and Fermi that, according to Abraham Pais in an article on Uhlenbeck in the December 1989 Physics Today, proved critical to Fermi's career.
Uhlenbeck became interested in Dutch cultural history and his first publication, written in Rome, was a historical piece on Johannes Heckius. Upon his return to Holland in 1925, Uhlenbeck considered becoming a historian, establishing contact at Leiden with the influential medieval historian Johan Huizinga.
At Ehrenfest's urging, Uhlenbeck teamed up with another graduate student, Samuel Goudsmit, in the fall of 1925, a collaboration which invigorated his interest in physics. Their work in the decoding of atomic spectra led rapidly to a discovery of electron spin, which proved to be an essential building block for modern particle physics and thrust the young graduate student into the scientific spotlight.
In 1925 Uhlenbeck immigrated to the United States to join the faculty at the University of Michigan. He returned to the Netherlands from 1935 to 1939 to teach the first courses ever offered in nuclear physics at the University of Utrecht. The decade of the 1940s saw Uhlenbeck back in the United States, dividing his time between teaching responsibilities at Michigan and, from 1942 to 1945, directing classified radar research at the Radiation Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Uhlenbeck remained an important figure in physics at the University of Michigan until his 1960 move to Rockefeller University, from which he retired in 1974.
Uhlenbeck's ties with the Netherlands remained strong throughout his career. In 1954 he became the first Lorentz Visiting Professor of Physics at the University of Leiden; additionally, in 1963, he was named the first Van der Waals Visiting Professor of Theoretical Physics at the University of Amsterdam. In 1977 the Dutch government honored him by making him a Commander of the Order of Orange-Nassau, the highest non-military honor it can give to non-citizens.
Along with numerous honorary degrees, Uhlenbeck was awarded several medals in recognition of his contributions to the field of theoretical physics: the Max Planck medal in 1964, the Lorentz medal in 1970, and the National Medal of Science in 1977. George Eugène Uhlenbeck died on 31 October 1988, in Boulder, Colorado.
The George Uhlenbeck papers, measuring 7 linear feet span the years 1918 to 1982, with the bulk covering the period 1925 to 1970. The papers are arranged in six series: Correspondence, Lectures and Speeches, Publications, Notebooks and Exams, Research Papers, and Topical. They document a lengthy career as both a physicist of international renown and an active teacher and collaborator.
Subjects:
American Institute of Physics.; American Physical Society.; National socialism and science.; Nuclear physics.; Physics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Ehrenfest, Paul, 1880-1933.; Goudsmit, Samuel A. (Samuel Abraham), 1902-1978; Kac, Mark.; Klein, Martin J.; Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1904-1967.; Pauli, Wolfgang, 1900-1958.
- Biographical information
  - Biography 1942-1946, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Certificates and clippings 1940, 1944, 1946, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series, containing both incoming and outgoing correspondence, is divided into two subseries: Chronological and Alphabetical.
  - Chronological
    The first subseries is arranged chronologically and covers the period 1926 to 1981. The bulk of this correspondence includes technical discussions of ongoing research in nuclear physics with colleagues from around the world, evaluations of the work of students, and correspondence regarding guest lectureships and visiting professorships. This subseries provides valuable insight into the development of nuclear physics in the middle of the 20th century, as well as the academic obligations of a university faculty member. Additionally, there are letters from the decades of the 1930s and 1940s to and from European scientists assessing the effects of the rise of National Socialism in Germany on European physics. The bulk of the earlier correspondence is in Dutch and German.
    - 1926-1964, 22 folders (Box 1)
    - 1965-1967, 1971, 1973-1982 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - Alphabetical
    The second subseries of the Correspondence series is arranged alphabetically by the correspondent. These include Uhlenbeck's mentor, Paul Ehrenfest, his first collaborator, Samuel Goudsmit, and other significant collaborators and figures in physics with whom Uhlenbeck carried on extensive communication. Additionally, there is extensive documentation of Uhlenbeck's role as an editor and reviewer for the publications of both the American Physical Society and the American Institute of Physics.
    - American Institute of Physics, editor (Joseph E. Mayer) 1938-1947 (Box 1)
    - American Physical Society, editors (John T. Tate, E.L. Hill, and J.W. Buchta) 1931-1947 (Box 1)
    - Deferment letters 1941, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Duffendack, O. S. 1945-1947, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Ehrenfest, Paul 1922-1932 (Box 1)
    - Foch, James D. 1970-1975 (Box 1)
    - Ford, George 1985 (Box 1)
    - Fox, Ronald 1970-1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Goudsmit, Samuel
      - 1925-1937 (Box 2)
      - 1946, 1951, 1954-1957 (Box 2)
        lacks 1955
    - Guggenheim Fellowships 1957-1960 (Box 2)
      lacks 1958
    - Hemmer, Per Christian 1963 (Box 2)
    - Kac, Mark 1943-1974, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Klein, Martin J. 1955-1960 (Box 2)
    - Konopinski, Emil 1977 (Box 2)
    - Ming-Chen, Wang and family 1978-1980 (Box 2)
    - Mott-Smith, H.H. 1952-1954 (Box 2)
    - National Academy of Sciences 1955 (Box 2)
    - Nobel Committee for Physics 1946-1952 (Box 2)
    - Oppenheimer, J. Robert 1926-1957 (Box 2)
    - Pauli, Wolfgang 1938-1942 (Box 2)
    - Putterman, Seth 1971-1981, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Rittner, E.S. 1948-1952 (Box 2)
    - Szu, H. Harold 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Uhlenbeck, O. (son of G.U.) undated (Box 2)
- Lectures and Speeches
  Lectures and Speeches document Uhlenbeck's rich career as an orator. These are arranged by title, where a title is given, or according to the event at which he spoke. A predominating theme in many of Uhlenbeck's presentations is the importance of understanding the history of physics and the need for effective collaboration within the field.
  - Boltzmann equation 1957 (Box 2)
  - Boulder lectures undated (Box 2)
  - Conference on statistical mechanics 1966 (Box 2)
  - "Die entropy der welt ist constant": temperature and heat lecture undated (Box 2)
  - Ehrenfest, Paul, reminiscences about 1956 (Box 2)
  - Einstein, Alfred, reminiscences about undated (Box 2)
  - Electron spin, 50th anniversary of discovery by Uhlenbeck and Goudsmit 1976 (Box 2)
  - Equilibrium undated (Box 2)
  - Introduction to quantum theory undated (Box 2)
  - Is there a direction in time? 1956-1974 (Box 2)
  - Laws of thermodynamics undated (Box 2)
  - Liquid helium undated (Box 2)
  - Max Planck award, acceptance speech 1964 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous lectures 1950-1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Outline of statistical mechanics 1967 (Box 3)
  - Principles of thermodynamics and statistical mechanics 1973 (Box 3)
  - So-called elementary particles 1954 (Box 3)
  - Some fundamental problems in statistical physics (Box 3)
  - Statistical Mechanics, lectures on 1961, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Statistical mechanics of non-equilibrium phenomena 1954 (Box 3)
  - Summarizing remarks at Copenhagen Physics Conference 1967 (Box 3)
  - Theory of critical point undated (Box 3)
  - Theory of phase transitions 1974 (Box 3)
- Notebooks and Exams
  The Notebooks and Exams series documents Uhlenbeck's contribution in physics education. The exams covers the 1940s and 1950s, in which Uhlenbeck was a professor at the University of Michigan. The content of the notebooks is technical, containing chiefly calculations and notes for courses on statistical and quantum mechanics, kinetic theory of matter, and nuclear physics.
  - Exams
    - Electricity and Magnetism 1941, 1949-1950, 1955-1957 (Box 3)
    - Quantum Mechanics 1946, 1950-1953, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Thermodynamics and Statistical Mechanics 1940-1949, 1952-1958 (Box 3)
      (lacks 1953 and 1955)
  - Notebooks
    - 1918-1930 Unnumbered, 12 volumes (Box 3)
    - 1928-1929 Partial Differential Equations I-III (Box 3)
    - 1928-1935 Statistical Mechanics I-IV (Box 4)
    - 1929-1933 Unnumbered, 3 volumes (Box 4)
    - 1932-circa 1971 I-VII (Box 4)
    - 1932-circa 1971 VIII-XV (Box 4)
    - 1932-circa 1971 XVI-XXXII (Box 5)
    - 1935-1938 Unnumbered, 5 volumes (Box 5)
    - Fall 1952-January 1967 Miscellaneous dates, 6 volumes (Box 5)
    - Undated (High school), 2 volumes (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous undated, 2 volumes (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous undated, 2 volumes (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous undated, 6 volumes (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous notes taken by students undated, 3 volumes (Box 6)
- Publications
  The Publications series is also divided into two subseries. The first contains Uhlenbeck's articles, arranged chronologically by his wife with a handwritten inventory of each folder's contents. The second subseries contains a few of Uhlenbeck's monographs, also arranged chronologically by the date of publication. The researcher should note that there is additional published material by George Uhlenbeck in the library's collection and should consult the printed works card catalog for titles.
  - Articles
    - 1924-1942, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - 1945-1957 (Box 6)
    - 1959-1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Monographs
    - Threshold Signals 1950 (Box 6)
    - Technical Reports (Engineering Research Institute, U. of M.), 1954-1956 (Box 6)
    - Reprints, Studies in Statistical Mechanics 1962-1964 (Box 6)
    - Lectures in Statistical Mechanics 1963 (Box 6)
- Research Papers
  Research Papers are papers produced by Uhlenbeck at universities and under contract with the United States government and private agencies rather than published. They are arranged by title.
  - Basis of Functional Assumptions in the Theory of the Boltzmann Equation undated (Box 7)
  - Contributions to Non-Equilibrium Thermodynamics I & II 1969 (Box 7)
  - Ideal Bose-Einstein Gas, Revisited 1977 (Box 7)
  - Kinetic Theory of Phenomena in Dense Gases 1958 (Box 7)
  - On the Propagation of Sound in Monatomic Gases 1948 (Box 7)
  - On the Transport Phenomena in Rarefied Gases 1948 (Box 7)
  - Possible Origins of the Quantized Vortices in He2 1972 (Box 7)
  - Reprints of published papers 1927-1973, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Some Historical and Critical Remarks about the Theory of Phase Transition undated (Box 7)
  - Some Problems in the Kinetic Theory of Dilute Gases undated (Box 7)
  - Statistical Mechanics of Non-Equilibrium Phenomena 1954 (Box 7)
  - Thermodynamic Equilibrium of Rotating Superfluids undated (Box 7)
  - Transport Phenomena in Very Dilute Gases 1949 (Box 7)
- Topical
  The Topical series contains informally gathered folders of materials tagged by Uhlenbeck with various titles. Most are topics in the field of physics, and appear to be Uhlenbeck's work in progress that he might have intended to develop into articles or speeches. Others include papers from organizations Uhlenbeck contracted his services to, such as the Navy and the Rand Corporation. In addition, this series contains records of the Joint Committee of American Philosophical Society and American Physical Society, whose main purpose was to document the history of theoretical physics in the twentieth century.
  - Bibliography 1953 (Box 7)
  - Bibliography prepared by George W. Ford of Uhlenbeck writings 1924-1980 (Box 7)
  - Biography 1979 (Box 7)
  - Book reviews 1940-1980 (Box 7)
  - Brownian Motion in a Knudsen Gas 1976 (Box 7)
  - Clippings 1964 (Box 7)
  - "Critical Region" notes undated (Box 7)
  - Defense Department Research 1944-1946 (Box 7)
  - "Distribution Functions, Fluctuation Integrals" notes undated (Box 7)
  - Electron Spin, discovery of 1965-1976 (Box 7)
  - Goudsmit, Samuel, biographical information 1953-1979 (Box 7)
  - International Congress on Theoretical Physics September 17-21, 1956 (Box 7)
  - Joint Committee of American Philosophical Society and American Physical Society
    - History of Quantum Physics 1962 (Box 7)
    - History of Theoretical Physics in the Twentieth Century 1960-1961 (Box 7)
  - Los Alamos notes, various 1946 (Box 7)
  - Nuclear Physics Group 1939 (Box 7)
  - "One Phase Region" undated (Box 7)
  - Putterman, Seth, collaboration with 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Rand Corporation 1958 (Box 7)
  - Recommendations 1943-1960 (Box 7)
  - United States Navy, Project M604-6 1951-1956 (Box 7)